<speak version="1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/10/synthesis" xmlns:mstts="http://www.w3.org/2001/mstts" xml:lang="zh-TW">

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        歡迎來到演算法與資料結構篇。這是電腦科學的靈魂，也是區分「寫程式」與「軟體工程」的分水嶺。無論是面試刷題，還是 AI 時代的系統設計，這些基礎都是你的內功。
        首先，我們要學會「衡量」。程式跑得快不快，不能只憑感覺，我們需要一把客觀的尺。
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        <lang xml:lang="zh-TW">
          沒錯，曉臻，尤其是雲端計算是按毫秒計費的。演算法寫得爛，帳單可是會爆炸的。
        </lang>
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        真的，效能就是金錢。在雲端時代，每毫秒都是成本，我們需要一把尺來測量它。
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    時間複雜度
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Time Complexity...
    Time complexity estimates how the runtime increases with the input size.
    Reducing time complexity from O-N-squared to O-N-log-N can save hours of processing time.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    時間複雜度估算執行時間如何隨輸入大小增加而變化。
    將時間複雜度從 O(n^2) 降低到 O(n log n) 可以節省數小時的處理時間。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    空間複雜度
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Space Complexity...
    Space complexity measures the memory required by the algorithm.
    In mobile development, optimizing space complexity is often more critical than speed.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    空間複雜度衡量演算法所需的記憶體。
    在行動開發中，優化空間複雜度往往比速度更關鍵。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    大 O 符號
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Big O Notation...
    Big O notation describes the worst-case performance of an algorithm.
    O(1) space complexity means the algorithm uses the same amount of memory regardless of input size.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    大 O 符號描述演算法在最差情況下的效能表現。
    O(1) 空間複雜度表示演算法使用的記憶體量不隨輸入大小改變。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    常數時間
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Constant Time...
    Accessing an array index takes constant time, or O(1).
    Hash table lookups are O(1) on average, making them ideal for caching key-value data.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    存取陣列索引花費常數時間，即 O(1)。
    雜湊表查找平均為 O(1)，使其成為快取鍵值資料的理想選擇。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    對數時間
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Logarithmic Time...
    Binary search runs in logarithmic time, or O(log n).
    B-tree indexes in relational databases provide O(log N) lookups, which is why they scale so well.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    二元搜尋以對數時間執行，即 O(log n)。
    關聯式資料庫中的 B-tree 索引提供 O(log N) 的查找效能，這就是它們能夠良好擴展的原因。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        懂了怎麼衡量，接下來我們要有工具。資料結構就是我們存放資料的容器。
        Phoebe，在 AI 時代，我們對資料結構的選擇還是一樣嗎？
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        <lang xml:lang="zh-TW">
          基本的還是一樣，但因為 AI 檢索的需求，有些以前冷門的結構現在變得很熱門喔。
        </lang>
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        讓我們從經典的開始複習。
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    堆疊
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Stack...
    A stack follows the First-In-Last-Out (LIFO) principle.
    Undo features in text editors are typically implemented using a stack.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    堆疊遵循先進後出 (LIFO) 原則。
    文字編輯器中的復原功能通常是使用堆疊實作的。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    佇列
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Queue...
    A queue follows the First-In-First-Out (FIFO) principle.
    Message brokers like RabbitMQ rely heavily on efficient queue structures.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    佇列遵循先進先出 (FIFO) 的原則。
    像 RabbitMQ 這樣的訊息代理高度依賴高效的佇列結構。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    雜湊表
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Hash Map...
    Use a hash map for fast lookups based on keys.
    Distributed caches like Redis are essentially giant, networked hash maps.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    使用雜湊表來根據鍵值進行快速查找。
    像 Redis 這樣的分散式快取本質上就是巨大的網路化雜湊表。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    圖
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Graph...
    Graphs are used to model social networks and map routes.
    Kubernetes uses a directed acyclic graph to resolve the order of resource dependencies.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    圖被用來模擬社群網路與地圖路徑。
    Kubernetes 使用有向無環圖來解析資源相依性的順序。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    鏈結串列
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Linked List...
    A linked list stores elements in nodes, where each node holds a value and a pointer to the next.
    Linked lists allow O(1) insertions at the head but O(N) lookups, unlike arrays.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    鏈結串列以節點儲存元素，每個節點包含值和指向下一個節點的指標。鏈結串列允許在頭部進行 O(1) 插入，但查找需要 O(N)，與陣列不同。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    樹
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Tree...
    A tree is a hierarchical data structure with a root and child nodes.
    Binary search trees enable O(log N) lookups when the tree is balanced.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    樹是一種具有根節點和子節點的階層式資料結構。平衡的二元搜尋樹可實現 O(log N) 的查找。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    堆積
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Heap...
    A heap is a tree-based data structure that always keeps the minimum or maximum element at the root.
    Priority queues in task schedulers are typically implemented using a min-heap.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    堆積是一種基於樹的資料結構，始終將最小或最大元素保留在根節點。任務排程器中的優先佇列通常使用最小堆積來實作。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        接下來這個是 AI 時代的新寵兒。為了讓電腦「理解」語意，我們需要一種能儲存高維度特徵的結構。
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    向量資料庫
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Vector Database...
    Vector databases are optimized for storing and querying high-dimensional vector embeddings.
    This is the backbone of RAG systems for retrieving strict context for LLMs.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    向量資料庫針對儲存與查詢高維度向量嵌入進行了最佳化。這是 RAG 系統為大型語言模型檢索精確上下文的骨幹。
    有了結構，最後我們需要演算法來驅動資料。
    資料結構是食材，演算法就是食譜。只有兩者搭配，才能端出好菜。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    遞迴
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Recursion...
    Recursion breaks a complex problem into smaller self-similar sub-problems.
    Tree traversal algorithms are naturally expressed with recursion since each subtree is itself a tree.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    遞迴將一個複雜的問題分解成更小的自我相似子問題。
    樹的走訪演算法天然適合用遞迴表達，因為每個子樹本身就是一棵樹。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    排序
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Sorting...
    Efficient sorting algorithms like Quick Sort are fundamental for optimizing search operations.
    Merge sort is often preferred for stable sorts because it preserves the relative order of equal elements.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    像快速排序這樣的高效排序演算法，是最佳化搜尋操作的基礎。
    合併排序常用於穩定排序，因為它會保留相等元素的相對順序。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    動態規劃
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Dynamic Programming...
    Dynamic Programming optimizes recursive problems by caching intermediate results.
    The longest common subsequence algorithm, used in diff tools, is a classic dynamic programming problem.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    動態規劃透過快取中間結果來優化遞迴問題。
    用於 diff 工具的最長公共子序列演算法，是動態規劃的經典問題。
  </voice>


  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    貪婪演算法
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Greedy Algorithm...
    A greedy algorithm always picks the locally optimal choice at each step.
    Dijkstra's shortest path algorithm is a classic example of a greedy approach.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    貪婪演算法在每一步都選取當下最優的選擇。Dijkstra 最短路徑演算法是貪婪策略的經典範例。
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        Phoebe，面試的時候常常被問 Time Complexity，但在 AI 時代，我們真的還需要手寫 Sorting 演算法嗎？
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        Well, you might not write Quick Sort from scratch, but understanding Time Complexity is key to scalability. When you are retrieving context for a RAG system, choosing between a Hash Map and a Vector Database can make or break your query speed.
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        原來如此，所以懂 Big O 才能避免選錯資料結構導致系統變慢？
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        Exactly. Algorithms aren't just for interviews; they are the logic behind every efficient system.
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        演算法與資料結構是工程師的內功。練好內功，招式才打得出來。
        我是曉臻，祝你寫出高效的程式碼！
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        I'm Phoebe. See you next time!
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
</speak>
