<speak version="1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/10/synthesis" xmlns:mstts="http://www.w3.org/2001/mstts" xml:lang="zh-TW">

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        歡迎來到 SQL 與結構化資料篇。
        雖然 NoSQL 在前幾年很紅，但到了今天，關聯式資料庫依然是金融與核心交易系統的霸主。
        很多新人會問，為什麼不全部用 JSON 存就好？
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>

  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        <lang xml:lang="zh-TW">
          曉臻，因為關聯和約束 (Constraints) 才是資料品質的保證啊。隨便存的結果就是以後隨便壞。
        </lang>
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        真的。在開始 Query 之前，我們得先蓋好房子的地基。
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    綱要
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Schema...
    Database schema changes in production should always be backwards compatible.
    Zero-downtime schema migrations require backward-compatible changes, such as adding nullable columns first.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    正式環境的資料庫綱要變更應該永遠保持向下相容。
    零停機的綱要遷移需要向下相容的變更，例如先新增可為 null 的欄位。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    主鍵
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Primary Key...
    We use UUIDs as primary keys instead of auto-incrementing integers to avoid enumeration attacks.
    Composite primary keys should be avoided in favor of surrogate keys like UUIDs for better flexibility.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    我們使用 UUID 作為主鍵，而不是自動遞增的整數，以避免枚舉攻擊。
    應避免使用複合主鍵，改用 UUID 等代理鍵以獲得更好的彈性。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    外來鍵
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Foreign Key...
    Foreign keys ensure referential integrity between tables.
    Dropping a foreign key constraint without a migration plan can lead to orphaned records and data corruption.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    外來鍵確保資料表之間的參考完整性。
    在沒有遷移計畫的情況下刪除外來鍵約束，可能導致孤立記錄和資料損毀。
  </voice>


  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    約束
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Constraint...
    Database constraints enforce rules on the data in a table, such as NOT NULL or UNIQUE.
    Adding a check constraint prevents invalid data from being inserted at the database level rather than the application layer.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    資料庫約束在資料表上強制執行規則，例如 NOT NULL 或 UNIQUE。在資料庫層面加上 CHECK 約束，可防止無效資料插入，而不依賴應用程式層。
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        有了結構，接下來是操作。在現代開發中，我們更依賴 ORM，但原生的 SQL 優化能力還是很重要。
        Phoebe，對於查詢效能，你有什麼慘痛經驗嗎？
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        <lang xml:lang="zh-TW">
          N+1 問題。那絕對是效能殺手。一定要記得用 Eager Loading。
        </lang>
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        N+1 確實是效能殺手。我們來看看怎麼用這些關鍵字寫出高效的 Query。
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    查詢
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Query...
    A well-optimized <sub alias="sequel">SQL</sub> query fetches only necessary data, preventing database bottlenecks.
    Use parameterized queries to prevent <sub alias="sequel">SQL</sub> injection attacks.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    一個最佳化良好的 SQL 查詢只擷取必要的資料，防止資料庫瓶頸。
    使用參數化查詢可防止 SQL Injection 攻擊。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    連結
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Join...
    Joins allow us to reconstruct related data that was normalized across multiple tables.
    A LEFT JOIN returns all rows from the left table even if there is no matching row in the right table.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    連結讓我們能夠重建分散在多個正規化資料表中的相關資料。
    LEFT JOIN 會返回左側資料表的所有列，即使右側資料表中沒有相符的列。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    索引
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Index...
    Adding an index can significantly speed up partial matching searches.
    Covering indexes include all the columns needed by a query, eliminating the need to access the main table.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    加上索引可以顯著加快部分比對搜尋的速度。
    覆蓋索引包含查詢所需的所有欄位，省去了存取主資料表的需要。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    交易
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Transaction...
    Transactions ensure that a series of operations either all succeed or all fail.
    Use short transactions to reduce lock contention in high-concurrency environments.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    交易確保一系列的操作要麽全部成功，要麽全部失敗。
    在高併發環境中使用短交易，以減少鎖定競爭。
    除了寫 Query，資料庫的維運也是一門學問。Schema 不是設了就不能改的。
  </voice>


  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    ACID
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    A C I D...
    A C I D stands for Atomicity, Consistency, Isolation, and Durability.
    A C I D compliance is what separates true relational databases from simpler data stores when handling financial transactions.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    ACID 是 Atomicity, Consistency, Isolation, Durability 的縮寫。在處理金融交易時，ACID 合規性是真正的關聯式資料庫與更簡單的資料儲存之間的區別所在。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    死結
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Deadlock...
    A deadlock occurs when two transactions each hold a lock that the other needs, causing both to wait forever.
    Setting a transaction timeout is the simplest safeguard against deadlocks in production.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    死結發生在兩個交易各自持有對方所需的鎖，導致雙方永久等待。設定交易超時是在正式環境中防範死結最簡單的保護措施。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    遷移
  </voice>

  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Migration...
    Database migrations should be automated in the C I / C D pipeline.
    Always include a rollback script alongside every migration to minimize recovery time after a failed deployment.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    資料庫遷移應該在 CI/CD 管線中自動化執行。
    每次遷移都應附上回滾腳本，以在部署失敗後縮短復原時間。
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    正規化
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    Normalization...
    Normalization reduces data redundancy and improves data integrity.
    Third normal form eliminates transitive dependencies, but sometimes controlled denormalization is needed for read performance.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    正規化減少資料冗餘並提升資料完整性。
    第三正規化消除了傳遞相依性，但有時需要有意識地反正規化以提升讀取效能。
  </voice>


  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    檢視表
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    View...
    A view is a virtual table built from a saved <sub alias="sequel">SQL</sub> query.
    Use views to simplify complex joins and hide implementation details from the application layer.
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    檢視表是從已儲存的 SQL 查詢建立的虛擬資料表。使用檢視表可以簡化複雜的連結，並向應用程式層隱藏實作細節。
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        現在很多 ORM 都幫我們寫好 SQL 了，我們還需要懂怎麼寫 Join 嗎？
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        Absolutely. ORMs are convenient, but they can generate inefficient Queries. If you don't understand how an Index works, you might accidentally scan the whole table.
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        懂了，所以資料量大的時候，Schema 的設計和 Index 才是效能關鍵？
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        Yes. A well-designed Schema with proper Normalization is the foundation of a healthy application.
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>

  <voice name="zh-TW-HsiaoChenNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        關聯式資料庫很強大，但還有一種不同的選擇。下集我們繼續聊聊資料庫系統。
        我是曉臻，下集見！
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
  <voice name="en-US-PhoebeMultilingualNeural">
    <mstts:express-as style="cheerful">
      <prosody rate="+10%">
        And I'm Phoebe. See you next time!
      </prosody>
    </mstts:express-as>
  </voice>
</speak>
